<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>http://teamfloriduh.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://teamfloriduh.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 22:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 22:03:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>

    
    
    <item>
      <title>Curtain Call</title>
      <link>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/06/03/postmortem/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/06/03/postmortem</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been an insane month, but amazing at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s Health Data Consortium’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthdatapalooza.org&quot;&gt;HealthDatapalooza&lt;/a&gt; was a resounding success, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthdatapalooza.org/agenda/code-a-palooza-challenges/&quot;&gt;Code-A-Palooza&lt;/a&gt; challenge was no exception. Out of 60 team applications and 10 finalists, 3 teams were chosen as the 2014 winners taking home $35,000 in cash prizes. The three winners, &lt;a href=&quot;http://lyfechannel.com/&quot;&gt;Lyfechannel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accordionhealth.com/&quot;&gt;Accordion Health&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.karmadata.com/&quot;&gt;Karmadata&lt;/a&gt; each applied the CMS Provider Utilization data set in unique, sophisticated, and novel ways with beautifully designed dashboards and patient centric data visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we are thrilled to make it to the finals for the live app demo, unfortunately &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.teamfloriduh.com&quot;&gt;TeamFloriduh&lt;/a&gt; did not place.We did however gain the opportunity to work with a number of other open health data developer groups attending HealthDatapalooza and we look forward to these future partnerships. Our current platform integration plans range from social health insights to ACO mapping, population health management, and more. Additionally, we are allocating resources for FOIA requests to gain access to more open government health data sets. As a community effort, questions, comments, suggestions, and critiques are more than welcomed. Our growing platform is first and foremost for patients, consumers, caretakers, and data junkies like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a more personal note, we set out for this to be a community event, something that the social healthIT crowd could rally behind. We raised nearly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medstartr.com/projects/370-send-team-floriduh-to-the-code-a-palooza-finals-and-help-to-fillthevoid&quot;&gt;$6k through Medstartr&lt;/a&gt; and other donationation, and collaborated with countless friends, family and colleagues to put together a true community effort. We wanted to reach people outside of the healthcare community and show them the interesting and innovative projects coming out of private and public collaboration. The good parts of our health tech don’t get nearly enough credit, and public outreach for projects like BlueButton, Direct, and open data sets are non existant. Today, two months after all this started, I have my cousin’s uncle’s brother’s father calling me up, and asking me about electronic health data access through the VA. People I hardly know are taking an interest in open health data, and that alone is a huge win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a technical note, we really wanted to focus on data visualizations, not dashboards, sliders and d3js, so all the data analysis was done in R programing language, and python for the visualization. You can see our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/laurenstill/team-floriduh-health-datapalooza-codeathon-presentation&quot;&gt;deck here&lt;/a&gt; and some sample hi-res renderings &lt;a href=&quot;http://imgur.com/a/hoTgK&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and as always, our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/laurenstill?tab=repositories&quot;&gt;code is open sourced&lt;/a&gt;. The rest of the website will be updated, with all the live renderings and some more functionality in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been remotely possible without the help and support of the #HITsm community, and for that we are incredibly grateful. Thank you letters/perks/etc are in the mail, I promise! Everyone talking about how hard the “tech” problems are in healthcare, but it really boils down to personalities and politics. The community collaboration on this project gives me much hope for the forward progress of our healthcare system. We look forward to working with others in the open health data space, and as always welcome anyone who wishes to contribute however they may.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, as always, a very special thanks to both Mandi and Nick who brought talent, insight and energy in spades. It was an honor to work with such brilliant teammates, there are no words that can truly express my gratitude for their selfless contributions to this project both personally and professionally. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>MedStartr Pitch!</title>
      <link>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/05/20/medstartr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/05/20/medstartr</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Things are starting to take shape for the TeamFloriduh team. We have just over 10 days to go before showtime, and are refining models, our renderings, annoying CSS and fine tuning a pitch. We’ve been looking closely at incorporating the BlueButton API, or possibly Direct protocol for patient data V/D/T. We’re holding off on both (as of this writing, who knows what will happen tomorrow) until we can confidently button everything up with proper data encryption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, we’ve started planning for some long(er) term hosting, CPT code licensing, travel, competent webdev outsourcing, data costs and more. To help with these expenses, and to launch the long term FloriData plan, we’ve taken to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medstartr.com/projects/370-send-team-floriduh-to-the-code-a-palooza-finals-and-help-to-fillthevoid&quot;&gt;MedStartr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can help us out by donating, spreading our message, or just sending some warm vibes our way &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medstartr.com/projects/370-send-team-floriduh-to-the-code-a-palooza-finals-and-help-to-fillthevoid&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/teamfloriduh&quot;&gt;TeamFloriduh&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter or visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthdataconsortium.org&quot;&gt;teamfloriduh.com&lt;/a&gt; for updates and for more information on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthdataconsortium.org&quot;&gt;HealthDatapalooza&lt;/a&gt;, visit healthdatapalooza.org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact Information: FloriDATA Foundation, Inc. 2220 W CR 210 Ste 108-322 Saint Johns, FL 32259 (904) 626-1633&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello Finals</title>
      <link>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/05/07/pr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/05/07/pr</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Independent Health IT Vets Create Team FloriDUH to #FillTheVoid Against Big Health at Health Datapalooza&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Still, Kypreos, Bishop team up to compete against established industry heavyweights at the 2014 Code-A-Thon event in Washington, DC&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacksonville, Fla. (May 7, 2014) – In a true-life David vs. Goliath battle, Team FloriDUH, a group of three independent contributors from across the country, has been selected by the Health Data Consortium, the Office of the National Coordinator, and the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services to compete against a number of leading healthcare information technology industry giants at the 2014 Health Datapalooza finals on June 1-3, 2014 in Washington, DC. Ten finalists were chosen out of a field of 56 applicants. Teams are vying for $35,000 in prizes, awarded to the most compelling data visualization application that makes use of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) Provider Utilization and Payment data set, released on April 9, 2014. Team FloriDUH was created the day the competition was announced and consists of three virtual friends, united by a shared passion for data science and analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the nature of the contest, Team FloriDUH cannot divulge specific information regarding its application, only that it is focused in part on what they call The Void. Finalists will be judged on consumer usability, visual appeal, and the application’s use of the required CMS data set. To meet these criteria, Team FloriDUH has created a cast of characters who will tell the story of The Void on stage at Health Datapalooza, essentially bringing their data visualization to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to facilitate future development on the open source data visualization platform that Team FloriDUH is building for Health Datapalooza, the team has formed a non-profit corporation, FloriDATA Foundation, Inc., and is presently filing for 501(c) 3 status. The Foundation’s goal is to provide open source tools, including APIs and REST service integration capabilities, to allow other entities or individuals to use the analytics application that Team FloriDUH builds, and to expand the analytics capabilities to incorporate additional data sets beyond the Provider Utilization and Payment data. The FloriDATA Foundation is set to launch a #FillTheVoid Crowdfunding campaign on May 9 through the healthcare-industry funding site, Medstartr. Their goal is to raise $10,000 over 30 days. The funds will then be used to acquire more data, optimize the hosting platform used for the application, develop additional application components, and cover the team’s travel costs to the Health Datapalooza event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Team FloriDUH consists of the following experts: Team founder and veteran health hack-a-thon participant, Lauren Still of San Francisco, a Navy brat whose formative years were spent in Pensacola, FL. Lauren is currently the Policy and Regulations Advisor for cloud-based Vendor Neutral Archive (VNA), DICOMGrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Kypreos of Seattle, team data scientist and particle physicist who previously worked at CERN and Fermila. He is currently an independent consultant. Nick and Lauren’s friendship dates back to their high school years in Pensacola. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Team leader and taskmaster, Mandi Bishop of Jacksonville, FL. Mandi is a partner in consulting firm Adaptive Project Solutions, Inc., and Chief Data Strategist for Surgical Momentum, LLC. She met Nick and Lauren via social networking, primarily interacting through Twitter about their shared interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name FloriDUH represents the teammates’ affinity for their home state, and the state’s (and its inhabitants’) tragi-comic reputation for bungling various government programs, such as elections and Medicare claims management. In addition, the name offers a humorous approach to the monumental healthcare system transformation task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For updates, follow Team FloriDUH, on Twitter @teamfloriduh&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;For more information, visit teamfloriduh.com&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;For more information on Health Datapalooza visit www.healthdatapalooza.org&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;For information on the Health Data Consortium, visit www.healthdataconsortium.org&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;For information on Medstartr, visit www.medstartr.com and on Twitter @Medstartr&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact Information: FloriDATA Foundation, Inc. 2220 W CR 210 Ste 108-322 Saint Johns, FL 32259 (904) 626-1633 www.teamfloriduh.com&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Toolkit</title>
      <link>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/20/tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/20/tools</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short post for now, but we are building a collection of resources and tools to help others learn and understand what we have done, and the technology behind it. This will be cataloged under the &lt;a href='teamfloriduh.com/resources'&gt;Resources&lt;/a&gt; section of this site. Hopefully, as we progress, will be be able to include tutorials, and examples based on the available Medicare data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking forward to finalizing our plan, and abstract for submission on Friday. #TeamFloriduh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The more I read, the more I acquire, the more certain I am that I know nothing.” ― Voltaire&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>First Insights</title>
      <link>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/18/demographics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/18/demographics</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Setting a benchmark understanding about how larger datasets behave can be difficult, especially when using new tools and technology. It’s important to get some basic clustering and visualization to understand the big picture before diving in. Today, we tested a few hypotheses that we could &lt;em&gt;reasonably&lt;/em&gt; expect to prove positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to make sure there are no surprises with the base case before adding on layers of complexity or information sets. For this initial investigation, we pushed the CMS data into a SQLite database, and ran some basic analysis with the R programing language. Specifically, we looked at the Medicare reimbursements and how they related to provider sex, age and race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, there was no significant difference in bill-out rates based on sex (looking at all the data), and it was the same with the reimbursement rate. This was confirmed with private data for race and age. Turns out, our government is pretty unbiased in how it pays out, and that’s worthy a footnote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align='center'&gt;&lt;img src='/images/mcrdemo.png' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Statistical thinking will one day be as necessary for efficient citizenship as the ability to read and write.” - H.G.Wells&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>First Look</title>
      <link>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/13/first-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/13/first-look</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week (April 9, 2014) CMS continued showing unprecedented transparency by releasing &lt;a href='https://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/Medicare-Provider-Charge-Data/Physician-and-Other-Supplier.html'&gt;Medicare payer information data&lt;/a&gt; for the 2012 year. This dataset, 9M records in total, includes physician names and addresses in addition to CPT code frequencies over 10. For patient data security, it does not include payment data for less frequent treatments. Chances are, if you are a physician who has provided care to a medicare recipient in 2012, your billing information is included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This government data disclosure has &lt;a href='http://www.healthcarefinancenews.com/news/doctors-protest-CMS-data-release'&gt;raised plenty of eyebrows&lt;/a&gt;, particularly from physicians and provider advocates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We believe that the broad data dump (Wednesday) by CMS has significant shortcomings regarding the accuracy and value of the medical services rendered by physicians,” said Ardis Dee Hoven, MD, president of the AMA, in a statement. “Releasing the data without context will likely lead to inaccuracies, misinterpretations, false conclusions and other unintended consequences.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still others in industry question what value “normal” people would find in such a data dump, without the skillsets necessary to process information appropriately. Personally, this seems akin to doctors who don’t trust that patients can understand disease management or critically evaluate treatment options or diagnostic information. This information is another important step towards defining the “cost”, “value”, and “price” parameters in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our team dug into the CMS data set for the first time on Monday, and the shortcomings became abundantly clear. The yearly aggregated data came with significant limitations. As the brainstorming session went on, it became more and more apparent that any data trend analysis would have to wait, and we would have to focus on geographic parameters, and publically available heatmap data. In addition to this, the amount of clean up necessary is staggering: cities spelled differently, missing fields, conflicting demographic information, and on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMS is specifically looking to fraud detection, and consumer tools, but has tied independent developer’s hands by not providing granular data which could be married with weather, CDC/NIH or other time-based statistics. While this and other data dumps are a start, it is only a start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five years ago the means for complex data analysis were not accessible to “normal” people, but that is no longer the case. The private sector has come through, and provided access to the tools necessary for individual critical analysis. It’s important to support the public sector in meeting the community halfway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can have data without information, but you cannot have information without data.” - Daniel Keys Moran&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/11/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://teamfloriduh.com/2014/04/11/hello-world</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2014 &lt;a href='http://www.healthdataconsortium.org/'&gt;HealthDataConsortium’s&lt;/a&gt; HealthDataPalooza is this June in DC, and the Code-a-thon was launched last with week. This year &lt;a href='http://www.healthdataconsortium.org/challenges/announcing-the-code-a-palooza-challenge-at-health-datapalooza-2014'&gt;the focus&lt;/a&gt; is on how independant developers can leverage the massive &lt;a href='https://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/Medicare-Provider-Charge-Data/Physician-and-Other-Supplier.html'&gt;CMS patient claims and physician reimbursement data&lt;/a&gt; recently released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already many journalists and &lt;a href='http://omni.docgraph.org/'&gt;health data junkies&lt;/a&gt; have already started pouring through the nearly 9 million records looking for trends and insights that may benefit patients, payers and providers alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s official, I have started a team as well and we are beginning to kick around ideas, looking at data sets and talking logistics. Transparency is the name of the game, so I’ll be writing when I can about our experiences, insights, questions, tools, technology, and well, everything. I’m particularly excited for the technical journey, and documenting that as much as possible so others may follow our path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a few goals in mind, beyond pure health data discovery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have Fun: It’s important to show others, especially non-health-data-geeks that this can be an enjoyable initiative. Yes, we nerd out, but it’s not all TNG and pizza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be Democratic: Also important is educating others so that this may be accomplished by “normal” people. We are not professional programmers exactly, but we do have a vested interest in data. We feel it’s important to highlight that together our different backgrounds can create a whole greater than the sum of our parts, and that the tools used to accomplish this are widely available to the greater public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn Something: Me? I need to brush up on R, and webdev. Nick is a complete newb to the healthcare scene. Mandi is looking forward to technical nuts and bolts. We all have vastly different backgrounds and talents, and it will be interesting to feed off of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Provide Value: Core to this initiative is the opportunity to provide real value and insight to the greater healthcare community and the patients involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Win Big: Let’s be honest, now, cash money potential has crossed our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond this, we are pretty open. There’s a lot to discover, and we will take the next two weeks kicking around broad hypothesis before narrowing things down for a formal proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to expand more on our team, and what everyone brings to the table, but for now, meet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align='center'&gt;

&lt;img src='/images/mandi.jpg' /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Mandi Bishop&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A hardcore data geek with a Masters from FSU, and a passion for analytics, Mandi fell in love with BASIC and her PCjr early on. She continues to be a patient engagement advocate, health IT innovator and dreamer. Mandi is currently in Jacksonville, Florida. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src='/images/nick.jpg' /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Nick Kypreos&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A music school dropout, Nick pursued a PhD in Physics from UF. Eventually working as a data scientist with CERN, Microsoft and Amazon, he now hacks on challenging data sets. For fun. In R. Nick is currently in Seattle, Washington. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src='/images/lauren.jpg' /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Lauren Still&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jack of all trades, master of some, Lauren is a health IT generalist. Currently handling all things policy related for DICOMGrid, she fills her days talking to compliancy cats and avoiding picture opportunities. Lauren is currently in San Francisco, California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Remember, kids in the backseat cause accidents; accidents in the backseat cause kids.” -Jack Handy&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    

  </channel> 
</rss>